Records of the Barnum Museum during the tenure of Elizabeth Seeley
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Records of the Barnum Museum during the tenure of Elizabeth Seeley
1950s-1960s
Seeley, Elizabeth
BHC MSS 0017
1 manuscript box
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
The Barnum Museum building has gone through various incarnations since it was first opened in 1893. In the 1950s and 1960s, the museum collections were managed by Elizabeth Seeley (a Barnum descendent). Her organizational files represent a window into the museum's inner workings during that time period, just as it was turning into a recognizable version of the contemporary Barnum Museum.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donation of Elizabeth Seeley, 1974. Originally accession number 1974.09, came in with material that now makes up MSS 0016 and MSS 0018.
Biography
The building that now houses the Barnum Museum originally was constructed for the sake of the Bridgeport Scientific Society, Bridgeport Medical Society, and the Fairfield County Historical Society. It was completed in 1893, having been constructed by the firm of Longstaff and Hurd. (Longstaff and Hurd also constructed P.T. Barnum's last home Marina.) Both organizations existed before the building was built, with the Fairfield County Historical Society being founded in 1881 and the Bridgeport Scientific Society being founded in the year 1878. The Scientific and Historical societies, along with the Bridgeport Medical Society, made use of the building until 1933. Membership dues and subscriptions were not enough to pay for upkeep and the societies ceded ownership of the building and their collections to the City of Bridgeport. During the 1950s and 1960s, the museum element of these organizations was revived. Acting as curator, Elizabeth Seeley directed the museum and managed its collections.
Scope and Content of Collection
The contents of this collection are primarily research files maintained by Seeley. They have not been altered from the inventory conducted on the collection 1993. It is unknown if this is the original order.
Arrangement
Material has been arranged alphabetically. Due to small size, there have been no additional series added.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Barnum, P.T. (Phineas Taylor), 1810-1891; Barnum Institute of Science and History; Barnum Museum; Barnum Scientific Society; Fairfield County Historical Society
Related Collections
The Barnum Museum holds a small collection of documents similar to the material present in the Records of the Bridgeport Scientific Society (BM-MSS 001). See also local collection BHC-MSS 0006.
- Inventory
  - Addresses, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Association of Museums, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Architecture, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barnum Festival, 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Inventories of clothing, etc., 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gifts, loans and exhibits, c. 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Museum bird collection, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Books for sale, lists and catalogues, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Biographical information about E. S. Seeley regarding the Barnum Museum, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Additional papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Barnum genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - P.T. Barnum houses and furnishings, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - P.T. Barnum, biography, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - P.T. Barnum, East Bridgeport, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - P.T. Barnum, copies of Barnum’s letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Another Side of Barnum’s Life" by C.L. Pancoast, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 16)